Vasu Balakrishnan

Accomplished software development engineer with over 20 years of hands-on experience that includes analysis and design, architecture, development, and leading teams, building web, desktop, mobile, cloud-native applications and big data analytics. Passionate technologist dedicated to continuous learning and professional growth, mentoring talent, and improving development processes.

EXPERIENCE

Soros Fund Management, New York *Principal Software Engineer* — **2009 - PRESENT**

Soros Fund Management is a privately held family office fund that invests in equity, credit, macro, and fixed income markets worldwide.

Significant contributions include:

- Designed and built real-time dashboards for Portfolio Managers and Senior Leadership.
 Delivered in multiple platforms (desktop / web / native iOS) with robust drill down and visualizations, featuring P&L views, risk measures, compliance monitoring and security.
- Responsible for defining and standardizing the application technology stack (.NET Core, Angular, Azure Service Bus, Web Sockets, Redis) for the firm, with continued focus to leverage cloud services and migrate to cloud native architecture (containers, microservices). Worked with CTO and other senior technical leadership to set timeline and milestones. Worked closely with counterpart leadership within infrastructure teams to implement the appropriate technologies to support the current best practices around DevOps (JIRA, Bamboo, Git, Octopus Deploy) and security (entitlements).
- Built highly performant backend services (*Akka actors*), applications (*Angular*), data analytics (*pandas*, *numpy*, *pyspark*), and reports (*PowerBI*, *SSRS*) for multiple business units (*Trading / Operations / Controllers / Private Equity / Manager Selection*).
- Drove multiple PoC evaluating products, tools (Web Angular / React, Containers Docker / Kubernetes, NoSQL databases - MongoDB / InfluxDB, Messaging - RabbitMQ / Azure Service Bus, Monitoring tools - Grafana)
- Leading the cloud initiative to migrate on-premise resources to Azure. Partnered with Microsoft, Infrastructure, Networking and Cybersecurity teams to create a blueprint for setting up cloud resources, security, governance, reference architecture and best practices.
- Modernizing and expanding existing data analytics / compute platforms (*Databricks*, *Apache Spark*, *Delta Lake*). Identified key challenges in the current environment and future growth needs, drove the PoC partnering with the vendor, demonstrated the capabilities to multiple teams (*Risk*, *Quants*, *Analysts*) and rollout the new platform for firm-wide use.

Ivy Asset Management, New York Senior Developer / Tech Lead — 2005-2009

Led the team in design and development of core business functions (*Portfolio Allocations*, *Liquidity Calculations*, *Transaction Management*, *Manager Exposures*, *Compliance Monitor*, *Risk Limits*, *Statistics*, *et al*) and backend services infrastructure.

Cognizant

Tech Lead —1996 - 2005

Provided technical leadership for development teams on multiple engagements across industry verticals (Retail banking, Hospitality, Pharmaceutical and healthcare information solutions provider).

LANGUAGES

C#
Python
C++
SQL
TypeScript
HTML 5.0 / SCSS
Swift
R
F#

PLATFORMS

Cloud (Azure)
Server (.NET Core)
Web (Angular)
Mobile (iOS)
Desktop (WPF)
Apache Spark
Databricks
Docker
Kubernetes
Data Lake
Redis
Azure Service Bus
AppInsights
Splunk

EDUCATION

Masters of Computer Applications (M.C.A), Coimbatore Institute of Technology - India

Bachelor of Applied Sciences (B.Sc.), Coimbatore Institute of Technology - India